Okay today's דף daf is קידושין ע"א, Kiddushin ayin aleph, קידושין Kiddushin
71. We pick up in the middle of קידושין Kiddushin of ע"א
עמוד ב', ayin amud beis, 71b, six lines down in the wide
lines, line starting with the word חשמונאי, Chashmonai, the middle of the
line, אמר ליה, amar leh, and our learning should be for the
with the תפילות tefillot for the protection and security of the חיילים
chayalim and חיילות chayalot and all of our people in Israel and
anybody all the anybody who just no more loss of human life
and innocent life and God should bring a speedy end to this
war.
So we're in the middle of a story with רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda and רב הונא, Rav Huna, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda was called
for דין תורה din Torah in front of רב הונא Rav Huna
about having to do with a certain person that had visited פומבדיתא
Pumbedita and wound up calling רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda's attendant a name
and then it was heard that he was he would call people
slaves, so רב יהודה Rav Yehuda declared that he was a slave,
and this is all part of the larger context of כל הפוסל
במומו פוסל. kol haposel bemumo posel. And we we left off yesterday
was that that רב הונא Rav Huna said to רב יהודה, Rav
Yehuda, you know it might be true that שמואל Shmuel said כל
הפוסל במומו פוסל, kol haposel bemumo posel, but that means that something
you should be concerned about, not that you could actually go ahead
and declare this man to be a slave, and רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda said well what do you mean שמואל Shmuel oh and that
and then at that moment, excuse me, the man who they were
talking about came in and said how dare you call me a
slave I'm descended of בית חשמונאי, Beit Chashmonai, and רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda said אהא aha you see exactly as I said, because שמואל
Shmuel teaches that anybody who says that they descended from בית חשמונאי
Beit Chashmonai is a slave because the all of the original בית
חשמונאים Beit Chashmonaim died out and it was only a הורדוס Herod
who was a אדומי Edomite slave who identified with בית חשמונאי, Beit
Chashmonai, so now anybody who claims that lineage is actually a slave.
So there we go, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said I've been proven
to be correct. But now the גמרא Gemara picks up and questions
whether we should really trust this teaching. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this, אמר ליה amar leh so רב הונא Rav Huna said
to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, אלו סבר ליה מר להא דאמר רב
אבא אמר רב אמר רב הונא אמר רב, alo savra lemar lihad
amra Rav Abba amar Rav amar Rav Huna amar Rav, so don't
you hold of that teaching? Now this is of course a little
funny because this is רב הונא Rav Huna talking and he's saying
don't you hold of that teaching that רב אבא Rav Abba said
in the name of רב הונא, Rav Huna, meaning in his own
name, in the name of רב? Rav? So in the past here
שמואל Shmuel רב יהודה Rav Yehuda has been quoting all these teachings
in the name of שמואל Shmuel and here רב הונא Rav Huna
is quoting a teaching in the name of רב Rav who was
the classic sort of
בר פלוגתא bar plugta of שמואל. Shmuel. So anyway he says what
about this teaching in the name of רב Rav that כל תלמיד
חכם שמורה הלכה ובא, kol talmid chacham shemoreh halacha uva, that any
תלמיד חכם talmid chacham who is teaching a new הלכה halacha that
we haven't heard before, אם קודם מעשה אמרה שומעין לו ואם לאו
אין שומעין לו, im kodem maaseh amra shomin lo veim lav ein
shomin lo, if he teaches it before the relevant case has occurred,
you know you're willing to you believe it, he quotes a teaching
in the name of of of his רבי. Rebbi. But if he
only is teaching it very conveniently exactly when that case comes up,
then you're actually somewhat suspicious of it. Now this is actually quite
fascinating that we would actually think that somebody would make up a
teaching in the name of their their you know of their
רבי Rebbi in order just to respond to the case. In this
case actually it was not just that you know maybe this is
now we have a relevant case and I'm citing a teaching in
the name of my רבי Rebbi that you never heard before. But
in this case of course it was also being cited דוקא dafka
to defend you know the one who was citing it. רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda was teaching a position of שמואל Shmuel that actually came
not just applicable to the case but to defend the position of
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda who declared this person to be a slave.
Nevertheless it is interesting this like suspicion that the גמרא Gemara has
if you came up with a with a teaching of a tradition
that just conveniently is exactly about this case in front of us
and we've never heard you teach this before we're a little bit
suspicious about it. So therefore why should we believe this teaching that
you're telling in the name of שמואל Shmuel that anybody who says
that they're from descendant from the חשמונאים Chashmonaim is a slave? So
אמר ליה amar leh he said back to him, האיכא רב מתנה
דקאי כוותי. ha'ika Rav Masna dekay kivasay. Look I will give you
you know supporting evidence, רב מתנה Rav Masna holds like me, רב
מתנה Rav Masna will testify to the fact that this is a
teaching of שמואל. Shmuel. Now רב מתנה לא חזי לנהרדעא תלת עשר
שני, Rav Masna lo chazi leNehardea telasar shnay, it just so happened
that רב מתנה Rav Masna had never been in נהרדעא Nehardea where
this was taking place in the place of רב הונא, Rav Huna,
he had never been there for the last 13 years. ההוא יומא
hahu yoma by pure chance on that day אתא asa he had
come to נהרדעא. Nehardea. So here was רב יהודה Rav Yehuda saying
I can show you some corroboration of my position that this is
a teaching of שמואל Shmuel based on if you would just go
ahead and find רב מתנה Rav Masna and רב מתנה Rav Masna
happened to be passing through on that day. אתא asa so he
came in front of them in this בית דין beis din and
אמר ליה amar leh so then רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said to
רב מתנה, Rav Masna, you know how do you sort of ask
him the question without leading the witness? So he said the following
way, דכיר מר מאי אמר שמואל כי קאי חדא? dachir mar may
amar Shmuel ki kachada? חד כרעא אגודא וחד כרעא במברא? chad kara
aguda ve-chad kara be-mavra?
Do you remember the teaching that שמואל Shmuel taught that day when
one of his feet was on the bank of the river and
the other was on the ferry or on the bridge? I mean,
obviously, it's pretty memorable somebody teaching a הלכה halacha in the middle
of stepping onto a bridge. So that's how he prompted it without
suggesting or without being suspected of leading the witness. ואמר ליה, v'amar
leh, and רב מתנא Rav Masna said, הכי אמר שמואל, hachi amar
Shmuel, this is what שמואל Shmuel said: כל דאמר מדבית חשמונאי מוקא
חזינא, kol d'omar midebeis Chashmonai moga chasina,
anybody who says that I come from the house of the princely,
the kingly house of the חשמונאים, Chashmonaim, עבדא הוא, avda hu, is
a slave. Yes, of course I remember that. That was such a
memorable event when he told it as he was stepping onto the
boat or whatever, and he said that anybody who claims they're descendant
from חשמונאים Chashmonaim is a slave. דאשתייר מינייהו אלא ההיא רביתא, D'ishtayer
minehu ela hahu rivisa,
the only one who has left from the original חשמונאי Chashmonai house
was this young woman. דסליקא לאיגרא, de-silka l'igra, and when Herod was
taking over and had murdered everyone and so on, she went up
to the roof ורמיא קלא, v'ramya kala, she lifted up her voice
and אמר, amar, she said, כל דאמרי בית חשמונאי אנא, kol d'omarey
beis Chashmonai ana, ישתמע, yishama, it should be known that anybody who
says that I come from the house of the חשמונאי, Chashmonai, עבדא
הוא, avda hu, it should be known that they are a slave,
because basically they've all been killed out and Herod is the one
that's left and he's a slave, so anybody who makes this claim
is a slave. נפלה מאיגרא ומיתה, Nafla m'igra umesa, and she fell
off of the roof and she died. Okay, so there you go,
so he had corroborating
evidence, worked out very perfectly. So now רב יהודה Rav Yehuda is
shown to be right in addition to all the other ways he
showed up רב הונא Rav Huna in this story. אכריזו עליה, Achrizu
alei, so they announced about this man דעבדא הוא d'avda hu that
he was a slave exactly as רב יהודה Rav Yehuda did originally.
ההוא יומא אקרן כמה כתובות בנהרדעא, Hahu yoma akran kama ksuva binardaa,
that day many כתובות ksuvos were torn up in נהרדעא. Nardaa. The
way רש"י Rashi explains it is members of this man's family, if
now if he's a slave, so all the members of his family
are slaves, so all the women that they married wasn't a good
קידושין, kiddushin, so they had to invalidate all those marriages. Of course,
there's a little bit of a problem with this because he's only
testifying about himself, there's no external evidence and objective evidence, so why
is he believed to invalidate the other members of his family? So
there is one commentator who says that no, the כתובות ksuvos that
are being torn up is because he was a signatory on those
כתובות ksuvos and now he's פסול, pasul, so his testimony is פסול.
pasul. But anyway, it sounds like it was more drastic than that.
It wasn't just that they had to rewrite a כתובה, ksuva, that
he was really destroying these marriages as a result of this, because
as the story continues. Okay, כי קא נפיק, ki ka nafik, so
as רב יהודה Rav Yehuda was leaving נהרדעא Nardaa to go back
to פומבדיתא, Pumbedisa, נפקי אבתריה למירגמיה. nafki abasrei l'mirgamei. So all of
these families that now he has destroyed the marriages of
because it's now clear that this man and his family members are
slaves, so they all wanted to run after him to stone him
and we're going to see they literally had stones in their hand
because now he has ruined their marriage. So
אמר להו, amar lehu, so he said to these the men who
were of the family
who
are now not validly married to these women because the men are
because they're all slaves. So the men, so he אי שתיקו שתיקו,
ei shtiku shtiku, if you're silent, be silent. He says, listen guys,
don't make it any worse. ואלו, v'ilo, if you want to keep
on making a fuss about all this, מגלינא עלייכו, maglina alaichu, I
will reveal about you something you don't want revealed, something even worse.
What could be worse? הד אמר שמואל, had amar Shmuel, another teaching
of שמואל Shmuel that שמואל Shmuel said: תרתי זרעייתא איכא בנהרדעא, tarti
zarayasa ika binardaa, there are two families in נהרדעא, Nardaa, חדא מיקריא
דבי יונה, chada mikarya d'bei yona, one is called the house of
Jonah, וחדא מיקריא דבי עורבתאי, v'chada mikarya d'bei orvasai, and one is
called the house of the dove and one is called the house
of the raven, appropriate to the פרשה parsha we just read, וסימנך
טמא טמא טהור טהור, v'simanach tamei tamei tahor tahor, and the way
you'll know about their ייחוס yichus is the one that is impure,
the raven, the one that's called raven, they are impure, their family
is
invalid, whatever they are ממזרים, mamzerim, slaves and so on, and the
one that is called pure is pure, presumably these were all from
the house of the raven. Now, it's again a little not totally
clear from this story how he could make things any worse if
they're already all decided to be slaves, but anyway, presumably, maybe it
was just a suspicion on the rest of them. Again, this man's
testimony maybe didn't halachically impact his other family members, they wouldn't be
believed, but at least it made it suspicious and he said I
can make it even worse for you I can reveal this. So
שדו עלהו ריגמא, shadu alahu rigma, so they decided what was better,
silence was the better part of valor there, discretion was the better
part of valor, they decided to not make a fuss about it
and they took all of the stones
שדו להו ריגמא מידיהו shadu lahu rigma mi-yadeihu and they threw the
stones down וקם אטמא בנהר מלכא v'kam itma binhar malka and it
made there were so many stones that they were going to stone
him with that it made like a dam, it blocked up this
river, the נהר מלכא. Nehar Malka. Okay, so that's the end of
that story. Now of course the question we should be asking about
all of this is that if he actually did know about this
family that it was invalid, why was he keeping it? information to
himself? And we're going to see more about that in a little
while, a very important principle about משפחה כיון שנטמעה נטמעה, mishpacha keivan
shenitma nitma, once a family's lineage has been submerged, you keep it
submerged. And that sort of is in tension, right now it seems
like we want to know exactly who everybody is. But remember, even
calling this man a slave only happened in response to the fact
that he was calling other people a slave. So we are going
to now sort of be moving into territory, even though this was
כל הפוסל במומו פוסל, kol haposel bemumo posel, oh maybe you're חושש
choshesh it, you don't act on it, he actually took it as
real evidence and it turned out it was true. Nevertheless, now there's
a shift back in the other direction, which is like just keep
things to yourself if it's not obvious that somebody's invalid, you shouldn't
be saying anything about it. And in the end that's, he kept
silent. Okay. So, but it's not all one direction, because now we're
about to go back and see a clear labeling of certain places
that they are problem. Okay.
מכריז רב יהודה, Machriz Rav Yehuda, so this same רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda announced, בפומבדיתא bePumbedisa now there argues is בפומבדיתא bePumbedisa others have
the גרסא girsa בנהרדעא. beNehardea. So it's interesting because פומבדיתא Pumbedisa is
his own town makes more sense that he is that he's announcing
it in his own town. But so far we've seen the problems
being בנהרדעא. beNehardea. Anyway, so either he announced בפומבדיתא bePumbedisa or בנהרדעא.
beNehardea. אדא ויונתן עבדי, Ada veYonatan avdi, these two people אדא Ada
and יונתן Yonatan it's been known that they're actually slaves, יהודה בר
פפא ממזר Yehuda bar Pappa mamzer and this man by the name
of יהודה בר פפא Yehuda bar Pappa was a
ממזר, mamzer, בטי בר טוביה ברמא סרוחה דשקיל גיטי. Bati bar Tuvia
berama srucha dshakil gitei. He's a very wealthy man and everybody thinks
like he has great ייחוס, yichus, but actually you should know that
he's a slave and he was offered a שטר שחרור shtar shichrur
a גט get a writ of manumission but he refused to accept
it because he thought too highly of himself because he has such
status but actually halachically it's a slave. So here רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda is proactively going ahead and identifying people's פסול. psul. Okay, so
as I said there's sort of there's movement in both directions. Okay.
מכריז רבא במחוזא, Machriz Rava beMechuza, רבא Rava announced במחוזא beMechuza that's
his town. So again makes sense that רב יהודה Rav Yehuda was
announcing בנהרדעא beNehardea רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda's own town. Anyway excuse me
בפומבדיתא, bePumbedisa, פומבדיתא Pumbedisa was רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda's town at it's
our גרסא. girsa. So רבא Rava announced במחוזא beMechuza which is his
town. בלאי דנאי טלאי מלאי זגאי, Belai Danai Talai Malai Zagai, כולם
לפסול. kulam lepsul. They're all have some type of invalidity. ממזר mamzer
עבדות, avdus, what exactly it was not clear. Was it maybe just
a lesser status but not actually an invalid status it sounds like
he really is invalidating them. אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, said
רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, גובאי גבעונאי, Gvai Givonai, and here more identifying
of people with problems with their ייחוס yichus with their lineage. This
town called גובאי Gvai גבעונאי, Givonai, you should realize that that's a
was a corruption of the name גבעונאי, Givonai, they're really
גבעונים Givonim and therefore of problematic status.
דורנוניסא Durnunisa is דרי נתינאי. Darai Netinai. That is so this place
called דורנוניסא Durnunisa is actually a way of saying the village of
נתינים. Netinim. So the נתינים Netinim and the גבעונים Givonim are the
same. So you should know by the name of this city that
that's really filled with these people of problematic lineage. So now we're
not just invalidating individuals we're invalidating whole cities of people or whole
towns of people. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, האיבו בי כובי
דפומבדיתא, Haibu Beikvei dePumbedisa, this place of פומבדיתא Pumbedisa there's this like
village nearby פומבדיתא Pumbedisa a suburb, כולם דעבדי, kulam deavdei, they're all
slaves. Okay, again so this is really troubling these broad labelings. Of
course it's somewhat similar to what it's said that like עזרא Ezra
did when he was coming with that that he identified all the
פסולים. psulim. So here they're identifying all the
פסולים. psulim. So that is going we're going to see very soon
a strong push to just keep it quiet but that's not what
we're seeing here. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar
Shmuel, said רב יהודה אמר Rav Yehuda amar skipped a line. No
I oh no אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel again back to
רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel. ארבע מאות עבדים ואמרי
לה ארבע אלפים עבדים היו לו לפישחר בן אימר. Arba meos avadim
veamrei lei arba alafim avadim hayu lo lePishchar ben Imar. So
four hundred slaves and some say four thousand slaves there was to
this person by the name of פישחר בן אימר Pishchar ben Imar
וכולם נטמעו בכהונה. vekulam nitmu bikehuna. And they all intermarried amongst כהנים.
kohanim. They were all and רש"י Rashi says the reason it is
because as slaves if they were slaves of a כהן kohen they
could eat תרומה teruma so they were able to pass themselves off
as כהנים. kohanim. So they all married amongst כהנים kohanim and therefore
now we have to be concerned that that כהן kohen might actually
not be a
כהן. kohen. So how much do we have to worry about that
or like what are we going to do suspect every כהן? kohen?
Okay so let's see. וכל כהן שיש בו עזות פנים אינו אלא
מהם. Vekol kohen sheyesh bo azus panim eino ela mehem. So now
saying oh and we have a way of identifying them. If you
see a כהן kohen that's brazen then you know
he's and
they're not a כהן kohen *Kohen*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* pushes
back. אמר אביי Amar Abaye, *Amar Abaye*, כולהו יספין בשורא דבנרדשא *kulu
yaspim b'shura d'Ben Ardas*. So first אביי Abaye *Abaye* says, and by
the way you should know all of these slaves or all of
these כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim*, these כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim* that are passing them—these
slaves passing themselves off as כהנים Kohanim. *Kohanim*, you know, all of
these—they can all be found in this like row, meaning in this
position of authority in נרדשא *Nardas*. ופליגא *U'pliga* now this idea that
they are—we should be suspicious of כהנים Kohanim, *Kohanim* that act this
way, argues דרבי אלעזר *d'Rabbi Elazar*. דאמר רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar *D'amar
Rabbi Elazar*, אם ראית כהן kohen. בעזות מצח אל תהרהר אחריו *im
ra'isa Kohen b'azus metzach al taharher acharav*. If you see a כהן
Kohen *Kohen* that acts with brazenness, don't suspect that they're not a
legitimate כהן *Kohen*. God forbid, how could a כהן *Kohen* act that
way? Maybe there's some פסול pasul *p'sul*, you know, invalidity in his
lineage? No. שנאמר Shene'emar, *Shene'emar*, ועמך כמריבי כהן *v'amcha k'mrivai Kohen*, your
people are like those that argue with a כהן *Kohen*, so you
see a כהן *Kohen* can—is, you know, can be contentious, because it
takes two to tango. All right, so anyway, right now we are
having a lot of labeling of people and suspecting of people and
so on with like a little bit of a pushback. But it's
gonna—the pushback's gonna grow. אמר רב Rav אבין בר רב Rav. אדא
אמר רב Rav. *Amar Rav Avin bar Rav Adda amar Rav*, כל
הנושא אשה שאינה הגונה לו *kol hanosei ishah she'eino hogenes lo*. First
we're going to finish with some of the אגדתא *Aggadetah* about marrying
a woman that is not proper for—for you, for you being the
man, and meaning of a lesser lineage. Anybody who marries a woman
of a lesser lineage, כשהקדוש ברוך הוא kshe'hakadosh baruch hu משרה שכינתו
*k'shehakadosh baruch hu mashreh shechinaso*, when God causes His שכינה Shechinah *Shechinah*
to dwell amongst the people, מעיד על כל השבטים ואין מעיד עליו
*maid al kol hashvatim v'ein maid alav*. He testifies, you know, about
the proper lineage of all of the שבטים shevatim *shvatim*, but won't
testify about or like or won't identify with—with this family. שנאמר *Shene'emar*,
שבטי יה עדות לישראל *shivtei Yah edus l'Yisrael*, the tribes of God
testimony to Israel. אימתי הוי עדות לישראל *Eimasai havei edus l'Yisrael*, when
is it testimony about their, let's say, being part of the of
ישראל Yisrael, *Israel*? בזמן שהשבטים שבטי יה *Bizman sheshvatim shivtei Yah*, when
they are tribes of God, meaning when they're all sort of properly
organized, the families and the tribes, and not when there is, you
know, it's become adulterated. Now again, what does it mean adulterated? Does
it mean marrying somebody of—of a lesser status but still הלכתית *halachically*
כשר kasher *kosher*, or does it mean actually marrying somebody of an
invalid status? It would be funny to say that it's not, you
know, שבטי יה *shivtei Yah*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* before when it
said like it's inappropriate to marry someone of a lower status, but
here in terms of sense of inclusion in ישראל Yisrael, *Israel*, it
would seem maybe we're more moving on and especially recent—the discussions about
being an עבד eved *eved* and a ממזר mamzer *mamzer* that we're
really talking about marrying, you know, somebody that really invalidates the family.
Okay. אמר רבי Rabbi, חמא ברבי חנינא *Amar Rabbi Chama b'Rabbi Chanina*,
כשהקדוש ברוך הוא משרה שכינתו *k'shehakadosh baruch hu mashreh shechinaso*, when God
causes His שכינה Shechinah, *Shechinah* to dwell, אין משרה אלא ela, על
משפחות מיוחסות mishpachot meyuchasot. שבישראל *ein mashreh ela al mishpachos meyuchasos shebeYisrael*.
It only dwells on the families of lineage in ישראל Yisrael, *Israel*.
A little different, before it sounded like God's שכינה Shchina, *Shechinah* might
dwell among everybody but only some are identified as God's tribe, God's
people. Here the שכינה *Shechinah* doesn't dwell except on the families that
are—have יחוס yichus, *yichus*. שנאמר *Shene'emar*, בעת ההיא נאם השם אהיה לאלהים
לכל משפחות mishpachos ישראל *ba'eis hahi neum Hashem eheyeh l'Elokim l'chol mishpachos
Yisrael*. That day I will be a God to all of the
families of ישראל *Israel*, לכל ישראל לא נאמר *l'chol Yisrael lo ne'emar*,
not all of ישראל *Israel*, אלא לכל משפחות mishpachos *ela l'chol mishpachos*,
okay, all of the families, all of those that have properly kept
their family identifications and their family יחוס yichus. *yichus*. So again, this
does not sound like we're limiting—we're saying like only to exclude those
that are פסול pasul *pasul*. It sounds actually like, you know, the
whole keeping of the proper יחוס yichus. *yichus*, you know, even and
the people of the right status, you know, marrying with others of
the right status. So obviously this goes a—very against our sort of
more egalitarian ethos these days.
So—so it says, לכל ישראל לא נאמר *l'chol Yisrael lo ne'emar*, it
doesn't say all of ישראל *Israel*, אלא לכל משפחות *ela l'chol mishpachos*,
all of the families. והמה יהיו לי לעם *V'heimah yihyu li l'am*,
and they will be for Me as a people. אמר רבה בר
רב הונא Rav Huna, *Amar Rabbah bar Rav Huna*, זו מעלה יש
בין ישראל לגרים *zo ma'alah yesh bein Yisrael l'geirim*. This is a—a
way a higher level that a naturally born ישראל *Yisrael* has over
a גר ger, *ger*, a—a convert. דישראל כתיב בהו *D'b'Yisrael kesiv behu*,
when it comes to the born Jew, it says, והייתי להם לאלהים
*v'hayisi lahem l'Elokim*, I will be for them to a God, והמה
יהיו לי לעם *v'heimah yihyu li l'am*, and they'll be to Me
as a nation. ואילו בגרים כתיב *Mi'ilu b'geirim kesiv*, when it speaks
to גרים gerim *geirim* it says, מי הוא זה ערב את לבו
לגשת אלי *mi hu zeh arav es libo l'higeshal elai*, who is
that that heart, you know, stirs them up to come close to
Me, נאם השם *neum Hashem*, והייתם לי לעם ואנכי אהיה לכם לאלהים
*v'hayisem li l'am v'anochi eheyeh lachem l'Elokim*, and you will be to
Me as a nation and I will be to you for a
God. Sounds like the same, sounds actually very wonderful, your heart has
stirred you up to draw close to God. Where is it different?
I'll be to you a God, you'll be to Me a nation.
So the difference is the order. When it says by the ישראל
*Yisrael*, it says, I will be for them for a God and
they will be for Me for people. So as רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
says, I've already have a relationship with them, and that relationship helps
draw them close to Me. So they start off with a benefit
that they're already sort of born into the system, so it's sort
of easier to draw close. Whereas somebody who starts from the outside,
you know, there, you have to first, you have to be have
the motivation to draw close. The system of the connection to, you
know, God and תורה, Torah whatever doesn't preexist to draw you close.
You have to first draw close and then God will be for
God. So read that way, it's actually sort of you know somewhat
descriptive and certainly speaks to the level that it requires, you know,
the amazing achievement of somebody for being a גר, ger, but it's
also the גמרא Gemara seems to also sort of be framing it
as if the idea, you know, that it's, you know, better, I
mean it's obviously, you know, that that speaking towards this sort of
hierarchy of status. And again, this is something that if you're higher
up on the hierarchy, this is a benefit that you get. But
you know you could equally look at it as a way of
praising the accomplishment of the גר, ger although I don't think it's
what the גמרא Gemara meant. Anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay,
אמר
רבי חלבו, Amar Rabbi Chelbo, said רבי חלבו, Rabbi Chelbo, קשים גרים
לישראל כספחת. Kashim gerim le'Yisrael kesappachat.
Now this is a really harsh statement, but we'll see in a
minute how it can get reinterpreted. Converts are as difficult to Israel
as a scab, שנאמר, as it says, ונלוה הגר עליהם ונספחו על
בית יעקב, Venilva hager aleihem venispachu al beit Yaakov,
and the stranger will accompany to them, like cleave onto them, and
will be added on to the house of יעקב. Yaakov. כתיב הכא
ונספחו, Ketiv hacha venispachu,
you will add on like a you know an addition, an appendage,
וכתיב התם לשאת ולספחת, Uchetiv hatam laseit velasappachat,
and when it's talking about the various forms of צרעת, tzara'at, it
calls it a שאת seit and a ספחת sappachat as a type
of a scab. So you see they become like a scab. Now
what does this mean, a scab? So רש"י Rashi says it's a
concern that because maybe they're new to this tradition and they're not
as conversant, they will lead other people astray, they won't be as
careful with the מצוות. mitzvot. That fits actually a context in the
גמרא Gemara in יבמות Yevamot where it's talking about being wary of
accepting converts. It doesn't exactly fit this context, so the best sort
of read within this context what תוספות Tosafot says is it means
that if you think that the שכינה only dwells amongst families of
יחוס, yichus. so a גר is not, doesn't have the same יחוס.
yichus And that's actually a very, you know, like harsh read of
that idea of יחוס. yichus But you know, but as we said,
that seems to limiting itself not just to a question of like
פסולים psulim and anybody did anything wrong by marrying, but really just
giving the weight to people on the higher social strata and the
weight to יחוס. yichus So I mean that's extremely, extremely harsh. And
therefore it's saying that if we have גרים gerim among us, then
there'll be a problem about the presence of the שכינה, cause then,
you know, in the sense of it won't all be משפחות מיוחסות.
mishpachot meyuchasot So this גמרא Gemara, has really been used by some
as a way, you know, like this to lead to a lot
of negative approaches, very strongly harsh approaches towards גרים gerim and you
know also very much about like Jewish genetics and משפחות מיוחסות mishpachot
meyuchasot and you know very harshly against major מצוות mitzvot like ואהבתם
את הגר Ve'ahavtem et hager and כגר כאזרח Kager ka'ezrach and so
on. But there are negative statements in the גמרא Gemara towards גרים
gerim and some people have really, you know, sort of embraced those
in practice and in פסק psak and so on. And then there
are other very strongly positive statements. So תוספות Tosafot very interestingly relating
to this statement here quotes an interpretation by a רב אברהם הגר.
Rav Avraham Hager. And he says, so somebody who actually was a
convert but made it into תוספות, Tosafot, and תוספות Tosafot actually quotes
it, and here תוספות Tosafot doesn't even say in the name of
רב אברהם הגר, Rav Avraham Hager, just quotes it as an interpretation,
excuse me, that the meaning of this is, is that the opposite
of what רש"י Rashi said. That because גרים gerim are so new
to it and they're so passionate and they've been drawn to it
and you know they're not sort of complacent about it, that actually
they show up all of the naturally born Jews who are not
so מדקדק במצוות medakdek bemitzvot as they are. So that's a nice
way of rereading this. But there's no question that this גמרא, Gemara
all this גמרא Gemara about יוחסין, yuchsin, you know does not at
all sort of fit with a much more egalitarian ethos that we
have and about משפחות מיוחסות mishpachos meyuchasos, and all of that. And
as I you know as was mentioned about in yesterday's דף, daf,
there's
obviously other ethos in the גמרא Gemara. particularly around תורה Torah as
the big equalizer, and by גרים gerim. as well there are statements
extremely you know positive ones and praising ones, and then there are
statements that reflect this you know focus on יחוס yichus. that are
much more negative towards גרים. How that works is anyone's guess. with
certain מצוות mitzvos of the תורה Torah is an important question. Okay,
so now we continue, bottom of ע' עמוד ב'. ayin amud bet.
אמר רבי חמא בר חנינא, Amar Rabbi Chama bar Chanina, כשהקדוש ברוך
הוא מטהר metaher שבטים top of ע' א' עמוד א', ayin alef
amud alef, when God comes to purify the tribes, so the simple
meaning of this is and again within this theme of like labeling
who's פסול pasul and who's כשר kasher, and this is where we're
going to come to the turning point on that discussion, when God
comes to purify the tribes and label who's פסול pasul and who's
כשר, kasher so שבטו של לוי מטהר תחילה. shivto shel Levi metaher
techila. He starts with לוי, Levi, God, he cleans out לוי Levi
first, שנאמר וישב מצרף ומטהר כסף, shene'emar veyashev mtzaref umetaher kesef, he
will sit as one who like purifies and smelts silver, וטהר את
בני לוי, vetiher es bnei Levi, he will purify בני לוי, bnei
Levi, וזקק אותם כזהב וככסף, v'zikak osam k'zahav v'chakesef, and he will
purify them as one would silver, gold and silver, והיו לה' מגישי
מנחה בצדקה, v'hayu l'Hashem magishei mincha bitzdaka, then they will be able
to bring to God, you know, the מנחה, mincha, the meal offering
with righteousness. So לוי Levi and including לוי כהנים. Levi Kohanim. Okay,
so אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, כסף
מטהר ממזרים. kesef metaher mamzeirim. Now רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi turns this on its head and he actually says money
purifies ממזרים, mamzeirim, which is a nice way of saying, so meaning
no, it is not that the purification is going to happen as
one would purify silver and by getting rid of all the dross,
but actually the money purifies them. Now what and they're going to
be made pure. Now that actually is a very dangerous type of
statement, right? It's like you know, you know, the money will כשר
kosher. it up, and how money can be used to overlook things
that should not be overlooked. What does it mean here by the
focus on money? So רש"י Rashi says it's talking about the fact
that people married into the tribe of לוי Levi because they had
money, we saw that before that people might agree to marry somebody
of a lower status and so on or of a פסול pasul
status for because of
money, and the point he's really making is not that the money
purifies them, that was historical, that's why they married into לוי, Levi,
or לוי Levi agreed to marry with them, but in the end
once they're married in and we don't know who's who, everything is
going to be fine. We'll just make it all כשר. kashers And
that's this approach like don't go looking to identify פסולים, psulim, our
job is to just accept things the way they are. Okay, and
so let's take a look, I'll give another read about that in
a second, but let's first finish this. כסף מטהר ממזרים, kesef metaher
mamzeirim, שנאמר וישב מצרף ומטהר כסף. shene'emar veyashev mtzaref umetaher kesef. מאי
מגישי מנחה בצדקה, mai magishei mincha bitzdaka,
what does that mean that now it'll be done in righteousness? אמר
רבי יצחק צדקה עשה הקדוש ברוך הוא עם ישראל, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak
tzadaka asa hakadosh baruch hu im Yisrael, that God did a righteousness
with ישראל, שמשפחה שנטמעה נטמעה. shemishpacha shenitme'ah nitme'ah.
This is with an עין ayin not טמא, tamei, but
like has been
you know a family that has somehow been intermingled is intermingled and
you accept it if people are לוי, Levi, they're לוי, Levi, they're
ישראל, they're ישראל, we just accept people's status as we understand it,
and if we know about some invalidity we don't talk about it,
you know, we just accept things the way they are. Their getting
mixed in כשר kashers them up. Not the money כשר kashers them
up, their getting mixed in כשר kosher, them up. And here we're
pushing back on all of that identifying of the פסולים psulim that
we had before. Now there is a very interesting read of the
way the money is מטהר metaher them, not just you know if
you grease enough palms you can get people to be okay with
things, but it seems to be the way the רי"ף Riff understood
this was because the way you are מטהר ממזר, metaher mamzer, the
way the גמרא Gemara says is that if a ממזר mamzer marries
a שפחה, shifcha, which is allowed, a male ממזר mamzer marries a
female slave, and then has a child and the child is a
slave and then you free the child, then the child is not
a ממזר mamzer because he went from being a slave to being
a
full Jew. So כסף kesef is מטהר ממזרים metaher mamzeirim because you
could use the money to buy a slave and to do this
whole device. So that's a creative read of this גמרא. Gemara Okay,
now let's keep on going. גופא. Gufa.
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, we're going
to go back to a teaching we heard at the beginning of
the פרק, perek, said רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in the name of
שמואל, Shmuel, again a lot of teaching here from רב יהודה אמר
שמואל, Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, כל הארצות עיסה לארץ ישראל, kol ha'aratzos
issa l'Eretz Yisrael, all lands are considered like עיסה issa meaning as
opposed to סולת נקי, soles naki, which was what the גמרא gemara
said when עזרא Ezra left בבל Bavel he left it like purified
flour, like sifted flour, all the bran removed, totally white pure flour,
okay, and therefore so it's only כשר, kosher. whereas if something is
עיסה, issa, once it's got dough, first of all dough was also
with bran and often the flour and it's water and it's yeast
and
it's
other things, and
it's eggs, so other lands vis-a-vis Israel are like עיסה, issa, meaning
that there are questionable statuses in terms of
ייחוס, yichus, וארץ ישראל עיסה לבבל, v'Eretz Yisrael issa l'Bavel, but ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael is Vis-à-vis בבל, Bavel, בבל Bavel was left like
סולת נקייה. solet nekiyah. All the פסולים psulim were removed, so vis-à-vis,
so in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they have פסולים, psulim, but presumably
they know who's who. Whereas בבל Bavel is even more pure than
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael when it comes to presumptions of people's status.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, בימי רבי ביקשו
לעשות בבל עיסה לארץ ישראל. bi'mei Rabbi bikshu la'asot Bavel isa l'Eretz
Yisrael. In the time of רבי, Rabbi they wanted to change that.
They wanted to say maybe things change over time and בבל Bavel
maybe has more questionable status than ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. אמר להם,
amar lahem, רבי Rabbi said to them, קוצים אתם מטילים לי בין
עיני. kotzim atem matilim li bein einai. You're putting thorns in my
eyes, because רבי Rabbi was descended from הלל, Hillel, and הלל Hillel
came from בבל. Bavel. So ultimately, you might think רבי Rabbi, is
the head of
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, like, yeah, we're the most חשוב, chashuv, בבל
Bavel is secondary. But actually, since he was descended from הלל Hillel
who came from בבל, Bavel, he said, this is actually undermining my
status by questioning the יחוס yichus from
בבל. Bavel. And רבי, Rabbi the whole tradition of the house of
רבי Rabbi was descendant of דוד המלך David HaMelech and so on.
So it was really important that nobody would question the יחוס yichus
there.
So רצונכם, retzonchem, if you want me to engage this question—I really
don't even want to engage it, but if you want me to
engage it—ייטפל עמכם רבי חנינא בר חמא. yitapel imachem Rabbi Chanina bar
Chama. Let רבי חנינא בר חמא Rabbi Chanina bar Chama go ahead
and discuss this issue with you. מיטפלי עמיה רבי חנינא בר חמא.
mitaflei imei Rabbi Chanina bar Chama. So רבי חנינא בר חמא Rabbi
Chanina bar Chama went and engaged the people who wanted to go
ahead and invalidate or question the status of people that came from
בבל. Bavel. אמר להם, amar lahem, כך מקובלני מרבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי.
kach mikubalni mi'Rabbi Yishmael be'Rabbi Yossi. This is the tradition I hear
from רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי, Rabbi Yishmael be'Rabbi Yossi, שאמר משום אביו,
she'amar mishum aviv, who said in the name of his father, כל
הארצות עיסה לארץ ישראל וארץ ישראל עיסה לבבל. kol ha'aratzot isa l'Eretz
Yisrael v'Eretz Yisrael isa l'Bavel. Okay, the teaching that we had before.
Now this is nice because if רבי Rabbi were to say it,
similar to the whole thing that came before about רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda and רב Rav הונא, if רבי were to say it, people
might be a little more suspicious because he is defending his honor.
So here somebody else said it in terms of their independent tradition
that they had. Okay,
and so yes, actually בבל Bavel has a higher status in terms
of יחוס. yichus בימי רבי פנחס ביקשו לעשות בבל עיסה לארץ ישראל.
bi'mei Rabbi Pinchas bikshu la'asot Bavel isa l'Eretz Yisrael. Similar thing happened
in the time of רבי פנחס. Rabbi Pinchas. אמר להם לעבדיו, amar
lahem la'avadav, he said to his servants, his attendants, כשאני אומר שני
דברים בבית המדרש, keshe'ani omer shnei devarim b'veit hamidrash, I'm going to
go to the בית המדרש—he beit hamidrash was the head of the
בית המדרש—I'm beit hamidrash going to say two things. Afterwards, I want
you to rush me out, okay. טלונני בעריסה, telununi b'arisa, rush me
out
in this bed or
structure, because that's how they carried him. He wasn't very
mobile. ורוצו, v'rutzu, and run. Because I don't want anybody to ask
me any follow-up questions. I want to say it and leave and
leave them with the ruling and not get any follow-up questions. כי
אתא, ki ata, when he went there, אמר להם, amar lahem, he
said, אין שחיטה לעוף מן התורה. ein shechita l'of min haTorah. There's
no requirement of שחיטה shechita for birds. התורה haTorah only speaks about
שחיטה shechita for cows and sheep or whatever, never speaks about it
for birds. הלכתא, hilchata, it's only רבנן. rabbanan. Now we don't rule
that way. We rule that דאורייתא, de'oraita, it's only אחד סימן, echad
siman, either the trachea or the esophagus, not
both. For mammals, it's two. But anyway, but he said it's all
דרבנן. derabbanan. And there is a position like this. Okay. So אין
שחיטה לעוף מן התורה. ein shechita l'of min haTorah. עד דיתבי וקא
מעייני בה, ad d'yitvei v'ka me'ayni bah, they were sitting and trying
to say, wait, what? It's not דאורייתא? de'oraita? And they were trying
to figure it out and get their head around it and look
into it. אמר להם, amar lahem, so he had them all distracted
and then he said, כל הארצות עיסה לארץ ישראל וארץ ישראל עיסה
לבבל. kol ha'aratzot isa l'Eretz Yisrael v'Eretz Yisrael isa l'Bavel. All the
lands are like dough to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael is dough to בבל. Bavel. בבל Bavel actually has better יחוס
yichus. than ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Now here it wasn't necessarily about
trying to say who's better, but by saying that ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael is like עיסה, isa, he actually is indicating that there are
some problems in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and people don't necessarily want
to hear that or if they do hear that they want to
know who's the
problem. Okay. נטלוהו בעריסה ורצו. natlu b'arisa v'ratzu. So his servants did
what he asked him as soon as he said that and he
had them distracted so it took them a while to get their
wits about them and to ask some follow-up questions. So they ran
him out on this stretcher. ורצו אחריו, v'ratzu acharav, and they ran
after him, ולא הגיעו בו, v'lo higiu bo, but they couldn't catch
up to him because he had got a head start. He distracted
them. ישבו בדקו. yashvu badku. So then they sat and said, okay,
he said that we're עיסה, isa, that means we got some problems.
So let's start looking into various families and see maybe are there
some people that are פסול pasul that we don't know about. עד
שהגיעו לסכנה, ad she'higiu l'sakana, until it led to danger, meaning where
רש"י Rashi says is they started finding out that some very powerful
families might have some questions about their יחוס yichus. and they realized,
oh, we better stop looking. Okay. ופירשו, u'pirshu, and they stopped. אמר
רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, היכלא, Heichala, by the היכלא, Heichala, by
the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, he's like taking an oath. בידינו הוא,
b'yadeinu hu, it's in our hands
to identify certain invalid families, אבל מה אעשה שהגדולי הדור נטמעו בו,
aval mah e'eseh she'gdolei hador nitme'u bo, but what should I do
that great members, people of the generation, have been assimilated into it.
generation that are intermingled in it. Meaning, so I know of some
פסולים, psulim, but I don't want to talk about it because it
would you know it would invalidate and affect the ייחוס yichus of
some major figures of the community. So now we are seeing again
this idea of, you know, keep it quiet. So very different from
what we saw in the previous on the previous דף. daf.
And again that that phrase of נטמעו בה nitm’u bah have been
intermingled. סבר לה כרבי יצחק savar lah k’Rabbi Yitzchak like רבי יצחק
Rabbi Yitzchak דאמר רבי יצחק d’amar Rabbi Yitzchak משפחה שנטמעה נטמעה mishpacha
shenitmeah nitmeah once a family has been intermingled it’s intermingled and you
just keep you know keep your own counsel at that point. אמר
אביי, Amar Abaye, אף אנן נמי תנינא af anan nami tanina we
also taught משפחות this is a משנה mishna in עדיות, Edyos, משפחת
בית הצריפה הייתה בעבר הירדן mishpachas Beis Hatzeifa haysa b’ever hayarden there’s
this family בית הצריפה Beis Tzeifa on the other side of the
Jordan, ורחקה בן ציון בזרוע v’recheka Ben Tziyon b’zroa and בן ציון
Ben Tziyon who was a powerful man, זרוע zroa with his arm,
right, he got everybody to say that they were פסול pasul even
though they really weren’t. He forced that through. עוד אחרת הייתה oda
cheres haysa and there was another one, וקרבה בן ציון בזרוע v’kerava
Ben Tziyon b’zroa and they were really פסול pasul but he used
his power and his influence to get people to treat them like
they were kosher. Okay, and then the משנה mishna goes on, כגון
אלו kegon elu families like these, אליהו בא לטמא ולטהר לרחק ולקרב.
Eliyahu ba l’tamei u’l’taher l’rachek u’l’karev. Things that were wrong and known
to be wrong אליהו’s Eliyahu going to fix up. So the one
that was פסול pasul that was treated that he forced people to
treat as kosher when אליהו Eliyahu comes אליהו’s Eliyahu going to rectify
that and make them פסול pasul again, and the one that was
kosher and made people treat them as פסול pasul. he’s going to
come and bring them close. Okay, that’s things that we know that
they’re a problem. כגון אלו, kegon elu, so now the גמרא Gemara
comments: like this, דידיען d’yedian
that we know that they’re invalid and nevertheless we’ve been treating them
as kosher. אבל משפחה שנטמעה aval mishpacha shenitmeah when it’s real lineage
has been intermingled and like exactly, you know, not known and lost
to us, at least lost without investigating, so נטמעה nitmeah we let
it stay at that status. תנא, tana, we taught in a ברייתא,
braisa, עוד אחרת הייתה ולא רצו חכמים לגלותה. oda cheres haysa v’lo
ratzu chachamim l’galosa. There was another one, another family that was invalid
and the rabbis did not want to reveal it. Okay, maybe exactly
for this reason. אבל חכמים aval chachamim but the way רש"י Rashi
says well let’s finish the sentence, אבל חכמים מוסרין אותו לבניהם ולתלמידיהם
פעם אחת בשבוע aval chachamim mosrin oso livneihem u’l’talmideihem pa’am achas b’shavua
but it’s passed down with a secret, you know, you know,
tradition, and they mention it once to their students every seven years.
שבוע shavua means every seven years, so there should be some record
and somebody should eventually remember it at the time of אליהו הנביא
Eliyahu Hanavi or something. ואמרי לה פעמיים בשבוע v’amrei lah pa’amayim b’shavua
and some say twice every seven years. Now the question is, whatever
happened to משפחה שנטמעה נטמעה mishpacha shenitmeah nitmeah once it’s been lost
it’s been lost. So that’s why רש"י Rashi says when it says
another one it means another like these that actually we knew they
were פסול pasul and we were being forced to treat them as
kosher. So on that type of a case it didn’t sort of
happen organically or whatever, there’s a sense of maybe we don't want
to allow that to get and was forced on us, we want
to keep a record of that. At least there’s that that seems
to be how רש"י Rashi is reading it. אמר רב נחמן בר
יצחק מסתברא כמאן דאמר פעם אחת בשבוע Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
mistavra k’man d’amar pa’am achas b’shavua it makes sense to say once
every seven years, not twice every seven years, that we really don’t
want to be talking about this stuff. Okay, and therefore the less
the better. כדתניא k’didanya like we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, הריני
נזיר אם לא אגלה משפחות hareini nazir im lo agaleh mishpachos
if somebody says, ‘I’m a נזיר nazir in the condition that I
will not reveal like problems with people’s ייחוס,’ yichus, יהא נזיר ולא
יגלה משפחות. yehei nazir v’lo yigaleh mishpachos. So as opposed to another
תנאי tnai where it says well you can choose either you do
it and you don’t be a נזיר nazir or you don’t do
it and you do be a נזיר, nazir, here we give him
a directive and we say accept the נזירות neziros and do not
reveal משפחות we do not want to be hearing about what you
know about various families. Keep it to yourself. Okay, so really quite
fascinating. And therefore if you’re going to say they did it I’d
rather say it was once every seven years rather than, like, the
less spoken about the better. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי
יוחנן שם בן ארבע אותיות Amar Rabbah bar Bar Chana Amar Rabbi
Yochanan Shem ben Arba Otiyos now that we’re talking about once every
seven or twice every seven years we’re going to say something similar.
God’s name of four letters, the י-ה-ו-ה Yud-Kei-Vav-Kei שם בן ארבע אותיות
חכמים מוסרין אותו
לתלמידיהם פעם אחת בשבוע
Shem ben Arba Otiyos
chachamim mosrin oso l’talmideihem pa’am achas b’shavua the sages pass it down
to their students once every seven years. ואמרי לה פעמיים בשבוע v’amrei
lah pa’amayim b’shavua and some say twice every seven years. אמר רב
נחמן בר יצחק Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak said רב נחמן בר
יצחק, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak,
מסתברא mistavra this sounds very familiar, it makes sense כמאן דאמר פעם
אחת בשבוע k’man d’amar pa'am achas b’shavua once every seven years, like
the less the better. דכתיב זה שמי לעולם dichsiv zeh shemi l’olam
this is my name forever. לעילם כתיב le’aleim ksiv like to keep
hidden. So since there’s an idea of keeping hidden, I mean we
already got that that it was once every seven twice every seven,
but there’s just like directive that you’re supposed to really keep it
as secret as like a type of you know like a secret
tradition a secret knowledge. So therefore I would like to assume it’s
only once every seven years and not twice. Okay,
רבא Rava wanted to teach it at the, you know, to the
תלמידים talmidim which is quite shocking, why he wanted to do that.
אמר ליה ההוא סבא Amar lei hahu saba a certain elder said
to him, לעילם כתיב le’aleim ksiv it said that should be, you
know, עלום שם ealum shem is by the way the Hebrew term
for somebody who is like anonymous. It should be hidden. Keep it.
keep it quiet. רב אבינא רמי. Rav Avina rami. כתיב זה שמי,
Ksiv zeh shemi, one verse says זה שמי לעולם, zeh shemi le'olam,
which we read לעלם le'illum to keep it hidden, וכתיב ukhsiv and
it says זה זכרי, zeh zikhri, this is how I should be
remembered. So why does it separate שמי shemi and זכרי, zikhri, my
name and how I should be known? אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar
Hakadosh Barukh Hu, לא כשאני נכתב אני נקרא. lo kshe'ani nikhtav ani
nikra. The way not the way I am written am I read.
נכתב אני ביוד קא, nikhtav ani be'yud keh, right God's name is
written in יוד קא, yud keh, ונקרא venikra but when we see
יוד קא ואו קא yud keh vav keh how do we read
it? באלף דלת, be'alef dalet, we read אדון. Adon. So this is
my name, but it's not the way that you refer to me.
You refer to me with the אדון, Adon, not with the יוד
קא ואו קא. yud keh vav keh. And the שמי shemi is
לעולם, le'olam, לעלם le'illum something to be hidden. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan.
בראשונה Barishona and now we're still on God's name, שם בן שתים
עשרה
אותיות, shem ben shtaim esre otiyot, the God's name, this was the
four letter name. There's actually a 12 letter name and even a
24 letter name which is even more powerful and more holy. So
God's 12 letter name,
so היו מוסרין אותו לכל אדם hayu mosrin oto lekhol adam and
originally it's shocking, every everybody was knew about it. Maybe again, maybe
they just knew what the letters were, I don't know if they
knew how to pronounce it, but it sounds like there was common
knowledge, I mean more common knowledge than יוד קא ואו קא, yud
keh vav keh, it's shocking. משרבו הפריצים Mishe'rabu hapritzim once those that
were like, you know, like not guarded, were increased, so maybe, you
know, people knew it but they were careful how and they didn't
use it. But then it was getting to be misused, not a
shocker there if it's common knowledge. היו מוסרין אותו לצנועין hayu mosrin
oto litznu'in they only gave it to very modest people שבכהונה. she'bakehuna.
Okay, I mean
presumably modest here meaning also that could be like trusted with the
secret knowledge. והצנועין שבכהונה מבליעין אותו בנעימת אחיהם הכהנים. vehatznu'in she'bakehuna mavli'in
oto bine'imat acheihem hakohanim. And they would use it for ברכת כהנים
Birkat Kohanim while all their other fellow כהנים who knew the יוד
קא ואו קא yud keh vav keh name but didn't know the
12 letter name, they were doing the ay ay ays during the
ברכת כהנים Birkat Kohanim and stretching out God's יוד קא ואו קא
yud keh vav keh name, the one who knew the super secret
12 letter name, they would weave it into the melody. But presumably
not that anybody else could hear. תניא Tanya we've done a ברייתא.
Braita. אמר רבי טרפון Amar Rabbi Tarfon פעם אחת עליתי אחר
אחי אמי לדוכן pa'am achat aliti achar achi imi ladukhan once I
went after my uncle to the דוכן dukhan for the ברכת כהנים.
Birkat Kohanim. He was a כהן and his uncle was a כהן.
והטיתי אזני vehiteiti ozni even though it was his mother's brother, והטיתי
אזני אצל כהן גדול vehiteiti ozni etzel kohen gadol and I tipped
my ear towards the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, that's
now that's I think a little bit of a problem because I
don't think Rabbi Tarfon lived in the time when there was a
כהן גדול, kohen gadol, but okay.
But anyway let's see what he says. Yes, so Rabbi Tarfon actually
lived in the time of Bar Kokhba, he was a student or
he was a student of Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai, so it's not
exactly clear here what he means כהן גדול, kohen gadol, maybe he
means an adult, maybe because he was a kid, I don't know,
but that would be funny. Anyway,
ושמעתי vshamati and I heard שהבליע שם בנעימת אחיו
הכהנים shehivlia shem bine'imat achav hakohanim that he like, you know, hid
the name during when his other all the other כהנים were doing
the ay ay ays and I was able to overhear this 12
letter name. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב. Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav.
שם בן ארבעים ושתים אותיות, shem ben arbaim ushtaim otiyot, God's name,
no the 42 letter name.
Now the even the even holier name, I think I said before
24, it's 42, excuse me. The even holier name of 42 letters,
that you only give before we just said the צנועים tznu'im of
the כהנים. This was only given to somebody who is צנוע tzanua
like, you know, modest or sec you know, able to keep a
secret, וענו ve'anav and humble, ועומד בחצי ימיו ve'omed bechatzi yamav and
has already reached half of his age, let's say he's 35 if
we assume 70 is the is the life expectancy then, ואינו כועס
ve'eino ko'es and would not get angry, ואינו משתכר ve'eino mishtaker and
he doesn't get, you know, drunk. Why is all these important? So
Rashi says because this is a powerful name that you could do
a lot of damage with, and therefore if you can't control your
anger or you get drunk, you might use it to curse somebody
out. ואינו מעמיד על מדותיו ve'eino ma'amid al midotav lets things go,
doesn't get like angry when people do things against
him. וכל היודעו vekhol hayode'o and of anybody who knows it, וזהיר
בו ve'zahir bo and is careful with it, ומשמרו בטהרה umeshamro betahara
and protects it in purity, אהוב למעלה ahuv lemala beloved above, ונחמד
למטה, venichmad lemata, you know, is is is cherished below, ואימתו מוטלת
על הבריות ve'eimato mutelat al habriyot and has awe of the creatures
upon him by not using it. You know, you have more power
by not using it than using it. ונוחל שני
עולמים venochal shenei olamim
and and and inherits two worlds, עולם הזה ועולם הבא olam hazeh
ve'olam haba this world and the next one. אמר שמואל משמיה דסבא.
Amar Shmuel mishmeih desava. Said Shmuel in the name of the elder.
בבל בחזקת כשירה עומדת Bavel bechezkat ksheira omedet עד שיוודע לך במה
נפסלה. ad sheyivada lekha bameh nifsala. Anybody who comes from בבל Bavel
you should assume they're kosher unless you know on what basis they
became פסול. pasul, Now this is a little funny because we've basically
just been assuming that everybody is kosher until we have a reason
to suspect them, you know, even though they spoke about this whole
thing about עיסא isa and so on. Like what does that mean
about an average person? presumably including ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, בחזקת פסול
הן עומדות עד שיוודע לך במה נכשרה bechezkat pasul hein omdot ad
sheyivada lecha bamah nichsharah is considered everybody's
considered invalid unless you know how they became כשר. kosher So you
can't like marry anybody who's not from בבל. Bavel. And now we'll
see that ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael fits in the middle of those
two. ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael מוחזק לפסול פסול מוחזק
לכשר כשר. muchzak lepasul pasul muchzak lekasher kasher. ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
if you know somebody's פסול pasul. they're פסול, pasul if you know
they're כשר kosher, they're כשר, kosher, which is like huh? So what's
the default? You know, בבל Bavel he said the default was כשר,
kosher. חוץ chutz everybody other than בבל Bavel he said the default
was פסול. pasul Which way does ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael go? You
have, so that's גמרא Gemara asks, הגופא קשיא, hagufei kashya, this doesn't
make sense. אמרת מוחזק לפסול פסול amartat muchzak lipso pasul הסתמא כשר.
hastama kasher. If you know they're פסול pasul. they're פסול pasul means
that the default is כשר. kosher? והדר תני vehadar tanei and then
it said by ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael מוחזק לכשר כשר muchzak lekashar
kashar הסתמא פסול, hastama pasul,
the default is פסול. psul. אמר רב הונא בר תחליפא משמיה דרב
לא
קשיא, amar Rav Huna bar Tachalifa mishmei deRav lo kashya, it's not
difficult.
Top of ע"א ע"ב, Ayin Aleph Amud Bet, כאן להשיאו אשה כאן
להוציא
אשה
מידו. kan lehasi'o isha kan lehotzi isha miyado. The difference is to
allow him to marry somebody, a woman, so the question is the
status of the man, or to force a divorce. Before you allow
him to marry, if this guy is from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
you're going to want him, you're going to suspect that he might
not be a good יחוס yichus, and he'll have to prove his
יחוס. yichus, Once he is married to somebody, then only if you
know he's פסול pasul can you invalidate it, can you invalidate him.
Now the question is what? A normal person even from ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael can't get married unless they prove that they're כשר? kasher
So רש"י Rashi connects this to a later משנה Mishnah that talks
about a כהן marrying somebody and assumed to be a בת כהן
Bas Kohen or so on. And תוספות Tosafot does the same and
reverses it in terms of the man and basically says we're just
talking about when you want to marry somebody of good יחוס. yichus,
You want to marry somebody of good יחוס, yichus if you're marrying
them from בבל, Bavel, then you know, if this guy wants to
marry a woman of good יחוס, yichus. or you could reverse it,
you know, but let's take it that way. This guy wants to
marry a woman of known good יחוס, yichus if he's from בבל
Bavel you assume that that's okay. If he's from other places you
assume it's not good. If it's from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael it
makes a difference whether it was before the marriage happened or after
the marriage happened when this issue was raised. But it's only when
they want to marry into a מיוחס meyuchas family. If otherwise, you
know, you don't, you know, normal person wants to get married, you
don't start saying prove that you have good יחוס yichus or something.
Okay, we'll see more of this when we get to the משנה
Mishnah later on. אמר רב
יוסף amar Rav Yosef כל שיחוסו בבבל משיאין לו אשה. kol sheyichaso
beVavel masi'in lo isha. Anybody that, you know, speaks Babylonian, Babylonian or
whatever, anybody that his language is the language that they speak in
בבל, Bavel, so you can assume he's from בבל Bavel and therefore
he has good יחוס. yichus. והאידנא דאיכא רמאי veidna de-ika rama'ei but
now that there are deceptive people and they'll learn how to speak
the language even though they're not from the land, חיישינן chaishinan then
we're suspicious and you can't use that as good evidence. זעירי הוה
קמשתמיט מיניה דרבי יוחנן. Ze'iri havah kamishtamit minei deRabbi Yochanan. Now זעירי
Ze'iri was avoiding רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. דהוה אמר ליה נסיב ברתי.
de-havah amar lei nasiv barti. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan wanted to marry
his daughter off to זעירי. Ze'iri. Okay, now רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
was from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, and you know, and the question
here was what we said that
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael didn't have as good יחוס yichus, as בבל
Bavel and he was from בבל Bavel זעירי. Ze'iri. חד יומא הוה
קאזיל באורחא chad yoma havah kaza be'orcha one day they were going
on the way, מטו לאורקמא דמיא matu le-urkama de-maya they came to
like a stream of water, ארכביה לרבי יוחנן אכתפיה arkvei le-Rabbi Yochanan
katfei so זעירי Ze'iri who was רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan student, carried
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan on his shoulders, he really saw himself as
subservient, he was the student of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So he
was doing all this to show this respect and obviously as a
student of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was a
little flabbergasted about
his persistent refusal. וכמה עברי ליה ve-kama avrei lei and he was
passing him through the water. אמר ליה amar lei רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan said to him, אורייתן כשירה oraitin kesheira our Torah is good
enough for you? The Torah of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is good
enough for you people from בבל? Bavel? בנתין לא כשירן benatin lo
kashiran but our daughters are not good enough? So מאי דעתך? mai
da'atach? What makes you think that you don't want to marry my
daughter? אילימא ממתניתין דעשרה יוחסין עלו מבבל ileima mi-matnita de-asara yichsin alu
mi-Bavel if from the משנה Mishnah of ten different types of status
that came from
בבל, Bavel, כהני לויאי Kahanei Levi'ei and then the rest of the
משנה Mishnah כהני לויאי Kahanei Levi'ei etc. and therefore you think
that like all the פסולים psulim left בבל Bavel and they're all
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and therefore you think בבל Bavel is
better than ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael he said that you can't infer
that from the משנה. Mishnah. אטו כהני לויאי וישראלי כולהו סליקו? atu
Kahanei Levi'ei ve-Yisra'ei kulu siliku? So just because it says that the
פסולים psulim came with Ezra from בבל, Bavel, it also says כהנים
לויים וישראלים Kohanim Levi'im ve-Yisraelim came with him. It doesn't mean they
all left בבל. Bavel. There's still כהנים לויים וישראלים Kohanim Levi'im ve-Yisraelim
in בבל. Bavel. So כי היכי דאישתיירו מהני אישתיירו נמי מהני ki
heichi de-ishtayarei me-hanei ishtayarei namei me-hanei so the same way there are
כהנים לויים וישראלים Kohanim Levi'im ve-Yisraelim left in בבל Bavel there are
פסולים psulim also left in בבל. Bavel. You guys are no better
than we are. Okay, so then the גמרא Gemara says
אשתמיטתיה ishtamititeih but רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan forgot, הא דאמר רבי אלעזר
had amar Rabbi Elazar he forgot he didn't agree with whatever anyway.
רבי אלעזר taught לא עלה עזרא מבבל עד שעשאה כסולת נקיה ועלה.
lo ala Ezra miBovel ad she'asah k'soles nekiyah v'alah. No, that actually
you know ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, בבל Bovel is is better, that
עזרא Ezra did take all the פסולים psulim out. He didn't take
all the כהנים, לויים, Levi'im, ישראלים Yisraelim out, but he did take
all the פסולים psulim out. Okay. ועולא איקלע לפומבדיתא. v'Ulla ikla l'Pumbedisa.
עולא Ulla came to פומבדיתא, Pumbedisa, remember פומבדיתא Pumbedisa was also from
the previous story. לבי רב יהודה, L'vei Rav Yehuda, and here we
go, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda again.
חזייא לרבי יצחק בריה דרב יהודה דגדל ולא נסיב. Chazyei l'Rabbi Yitzchak
brei d'Rav Yehuda d'gadal v'lo nassiv. He saw that the son of
of of רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, רבי יצחק, Rabbi Yitzchak, was an
adult, was already grown up and he wasn't married. אמר ליה מאי
טעמא לא קא מנסב ליה מר איתתא לבריה? Amar lei mai ta'ama
lo ka mnasiv lei mar itata l'brei? Why did you not find
a wife for for your son? אמר ליה מי ידענא מהיכא ינסב?
Amar lei mi yadana me'heicha yinasiv? I don't know where to marry
him off to? Because like I just as we've seen, רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda's very concerned about all this יחוס yichus stuff, and I
don't know you know who's going to be of good יחוס. yichus,
אמר ליה אטו אנן? Amar lei atu anan? So he said, אנן
מי ידעינן מהיכא קאתינא? anan mi yad'inan me'heicha kasina? So this is
a very nice pushback. It's like what, you know, you think oh
you know you're so pure, you know your יחוס, yichus everybody you
know you think you know all of our יחוס yichus is great.
So דלמא מהנך דכתיב נשים בציון עינו בתולות בערי יהודה? dilma mehanech
d'chsiv nashim b'Tzion inu b'sulos b'arei Yehuda? Look, we know that women
were raped during the period of the חורבן הבית. Churban HaBayis. How
do you know, maybe you're descendant of one of those women who
was raped? You know, what are you such a purist? Yeah, I
don't know anybody that's pure enough for my son. So he says
וכי תימא עובד כוכבים ועבד הבא על בת ישראל הולד כשר. v'ki
teima oved kochavim v'eved ha'ba al bas Yisrael ha'valad kasher. Okay, maybe
so, but even so, you know, a non-Jew and a Jew and
a man and a Jewish woman, the child would still be Jewish,
and I want to be careful even if that were true. I
don't know, I want to make sure my son isn't marrying into
somebody who might be descendant of a ממזר mamzer or of an
עבד or something like that, of a real פסול. pasul So ודלמא
מהנך דכתיב? v'dilma mehanech d'chsiv? But okay, there were others, you know,
things that were not so kosher in the earlier generations. So the
פסוק pasuk says here השוכבים על מטות שן, ha'shochvim al mitos shen,
that they they lie down on beds of ivory,
וסרוחים על ערסותם, u'sruchim al arsosam, and they s- s- putrid on
their beds. So what does that mean putrid? אמר רבי יוסי ברבי
חנינא אלו בני אדם המשתינים מים בפני מטותיהם ערומים. Amar Rabbi Yose
b'Rabbi Chanina elu bnei adam ha'mashtinim mayim bifnei mitoseihem arumim. This refers
to like this bad thing that's going to happen in the פסוק
pasuk refers, what it means it's it's putrid, people that urinate naked
in front of their beds. ומגדף בה רבי אבהו, U'migadef ba Rabbi
Abbahu, not the end of the story. רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu sort
of cursed that, said that's not a bad a good read of
the פסוק. pasuk. אי הכי היינו דכתיב לכן עתה יגלו בראש גולים?
Ei hachi hainu d'chsiv lachen ata yiglu b'rosh golim? Therefore because of
this terrible sin they will be at the head of the exiles?
משום דמשתינים מים בפני מטותיהם ערומים יגלו בראש גולים? Mishum d'mashtinim mayim
bifnei mitoseihem arumim yiglu b'rosh golim? Just because they urinate in front
of their beds, that's why they're going to be exiled? אלא, no,
it means something much worse than that. אמר רבי אבהו אלו בני
אדם שאוכלים ושותים זה עם זה, Amar Rabbi Abbahu elu bnei adam
she'ochlim v'shosim zeh im zeh, that they are you know they eat
and they drink with one another, זה
עם זה, zeh im zeh, ומדביקים מטותיהם זו בזו, u'madbikim mitoseihem zo
b'zo, and they you know push their beds right up against they
literally they glue their beds one to another, ומחליפים נשותיהם זה לזה,
u'machlifim nishoseihem zeh la'zeh, and they swap their wives one with another,
ומסריחים ערסותיהם בשכבת זרע שאינה שלהם, u'masrichim arsoseihem b'shichvas zera she'eina shelahem,
and they cause their beds to stink from semen that is not
theirs, because they're sleeping with wives that are not their own. So
if in the generation of the first בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, there
was all this adultery going on, so there's a lot of ממזרים,
mamzerim, so how do you know, oh, well I descend from the
Mayflower. Okay, how do you know that the people from the Mayflower
were so pure, okay?
So אמר ליה היכי נעביד? Amar lei heichi na'avid? He says okay,
I look, I accept it, fine, okay, I it's impossible to know
how pure we are, but nevertheless, I want I still want to
do the best I can. So what do you advise I do
if I want to find a family that I can feel somewhat
comfortable about that is a כשרה kashera family? So אמר ליה, Amar
lei, so by the way you got to like the again the-
see the ways in which the גמרא pushes back about the whole
hierarchy and genealogy and about God's שכינה, only משפחות מיוחסות,
and now it's like just let everything be, you don't even know,
you know, if you're a ממזר mamzer. or who you are, so
you know, just accept accept everybody and don't you know, don't try
to bring in all of this fake יחוס, yichus or יחוס yichus
that is questionable. Anyway, so it's really interesting to see the different
pushes. But he says okay, but I want to do something to
try to get a good יחוס yichus, for my son. So what
should I do? אמר ליה זיל בתר שתיקותא. Amar lei zil basar
shtikusa. Go by families that know how to- that are quiet, that
don't get into fights and argument and call people names and yell,
because רש"י Rashi the way רש"י Rashi at least explains it, I
mean you could sort of say if the גמרא thinks it as
being genetic, if you come from bad יחוס yichus. you know you
have bad מדות. middos. רש"י Rashi also says that people that came
from bad יחוס yichus, are probably used to having been, you know,
shunned by society and that cultivated in them more of an argumentative
type of an of a culture. Anyway, כי הא דבדקי בני מערבא,
Ki ha d'badki bnei ma'arava, so this is like the people of
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, interesting, even ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael also cares
about יחוס, yichus, might be a little bit below בבל, Bovel, so
כי מצו בי תרי בהדי הדדי, ki matzu bei srei bahadi hadadei,
when two families would fight with one another, חזו היי מינייהו דקדים
ושתיק. chazu hai minaihu d'kadim v'shatik. And they saw which one was
willing to be מוחל mochel and like stop fighting sooner and say
look, let's not fight, you know, rather than being so argumentative and
keeping it up. ואמרי Ve'amrei and they would say היי מיוחס טפי.
hai meyuchas tefei. Oh, the one that's more ready to stop fighting,
that has better יחוס. yichus, So it's really interesting because it becomes
a סימן siman for יחוס, yichus. but also there's now a shifting
and looking at מידות midos and not looking at יחוס, yichus. or
looking at מידות midos as an index to יחוס, yichus. but ultimately
you wind up looking at
מידות. midos. Okay. אמר רב שתיקותיה דבבל היינו יחוסה. Amar Rav shetikutei
deBavel hainu yichusa. The silence in בבל. Bavel. Families that are willing
to not, that are not argumentative, that's the יחוס. yichus.
איני? Eini? Is that true? והאיכא רב? Ve'ha'ika Rav? Didn't רב Rav
come to, according to our גירסא, girsa,
לבי בר שפי חלא, le'vei Bar Shafi Chala, this person who was
like, you know, poured vinegar. ובדק בהו, Uvadak behu, and he checked
them out. מאי לאו ביחסותא? Mai lav beyachasuta?
Doesn't it mean he checked out literally their lineage? לא בשתיקותא. Lo
beshtikuta. No, he checked out how argumentative or non-argumentative they were. Okay.
So really interesting way that becomes a substitute.
הכי קאמר להו. Hachi ka'amar lehu. And this is what he said
to them. בדקו אי שתיקי לא שתיקי. Bidku i shtiki lo shtiki.
Go check out if these people are, you know, quiet, silent, I
don't mean quiet, but whatever, you know, non-argumentative or argumentative. Okay. אמר
רב
יהודה אמר רב. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav. Said רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda in the name of רב. Rav's אם ראית שני בני אדם
שמתגרים זה בזה. Im ra'ita shenei bnei adam shemitgarim zeh ba'zeh. If
you see two people that are fighting, you know, one with the
other, you know, or like have a feud going on. שמץ פסול
יש באחד מהן. Shemetz pasul yesh be'echad mehen. So the reason why
do these feuds last between families? It must be that one family
has some invalidity in it, some, some, some, you know, scent of
invalidity,
scintilla of
invalidity. שמץ
פסול יש באחת מהן. Shemetz pasul yesh be'echat mehen. ואין מניחין אותו
לידבק בחברתה. Ve'ein manichin oto lidabek bechavertah. And therefore from heaven it
comes about that they are feuding so that they should not intermarry.
Now, that might work out better if you sort of said that
it was a problem of let's say a genetic disease that would
actually be a problem if one would marry with the other, they're
both carriers or something like that, right? If it's a שמץ פסול,
shemetz pasul, if it's about a question about status, about, like lineage,
then it should be a problem for any other family. But whatever
it is, you know, that is keeping them apart. So again, it's
interesting that the fighting and contentiousness now becomes, you know, an indication
of or starts to take, supplanting the focus on the actual יחוס.
yichus. אמר רב פפא סביא משמיה דרב. Amar Rav Pappa savya mishmeih
deRav. Said רב פפא סביא Rav Pappa savya in the name of
רב. Rav's. בבל בריאה. Bavel bri'ah.
בבל Bavel is healthy. That has good יחוס. yichus, מישן מיתה. Meshan
mitah. This place בבל, Bavel, מישן, Meshan, מיתה, mitah, that's like dead.
That's all bad יחוס. yichus Everybody there is like ממזרי. mamzerei. מדי
מידי חולה. Madai mi'idi cholah. מדי Madai is sick, which means that
it's mostly good people but there's some people there that have bad
יחוס. yichus. ועילם, Ve'Eilam, all these places are in Babylonia, היא גוססת.
hi goseset. Is like somebody on their deathbed, which means mostly they're
פסול pasul but there's some כשר people there. מה בין חולה לגוססת?
Mah bein choleh legoseset? רוב חולים לחיים, Rov cholim lachayim, because most
sick
people live. ורוב גוססים למיתה, Verov gosesim lemitah, die. So it means
which way the majority goes. So now we're back to naming places
and actually creating problems rather than keeping them quiet. עד היכן היא
בבל? Ad heichan hi Bavel? And now that we are talking again
about בבל Bavel being a better place for יחוס, we want to
know what exactly are the geographic boundaries of בבל. Bavel. עד היכן
היא בבל? Ad heichan hi Bavel? Where are we?
Okay. עד היכן
היא בבל? Ad
heichan
hi Bavel? רב אמר עד נהר עזק, Rav amar ad Nahar Azak,
until this place נהר עזק. Nahar Azak. רש"י Rashi says we're trying
to talk about the eastern boundary. ושמואל אמר עד נהר יוני, Ushmuel
amar ad Nahar Yoni, until נהר יוני, Nahar Yoni, because actually בבל
Bavel is bounded, the primary area is bounded by the Tigris and
the Euphrates and that's going to call it, be the place that's
called, you know, בין שני נהרות, bein shenei neharot, between the two
rivers. And now we're sort of talking about but beyond the Tigris
and the Euphrates, how far does it go to the east and
the west, and then we're going to do the north and the
south. Okay. So they debate between these two rivers. לעילא בדיגלת, Le'eila
beDiglat, northern, above within the, on the Tigris. עד היכן? Ad heichan?
How north does it go? Going up with the Tigris. So רב
אמר עד בגדא ואבנא, Rav amar ad Bagda ve'Avna, until those two
places. ושמואל אמר עד מושכני. Ushmuel amar ad Mushchani. ולא מושכני בכלל.
Velo Mushchani bichlal. Until this place מושכני Mushchani but not that far.
ואמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר שמואל מושכני הרי היא כגולה. Ve'amar
Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Shmuel Mushchani harei hi keGolah. מושכני Mushchani
is like גולה. Golah. Now גולה Golah normally means a bad thing,
it means exile, you know, but in this case, you know, גולה
Golah is another word for פומבדיתא, Pumbedita, which is pure בבל, Bavel,
like the good, good יחוס as we saw, you know, רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda was from פומבדיתא Pumbedita and he really cared about, you
know, and that sense of the purity of יחוס. So don't we
say that מושכני Mushchani is like גולה, Golah, is like
פומבדיתא Pumbedita is... How far does that go? עד היכא? Ad Heicha?
אמר שמואל Amar Shmuel עד אפמיא תתאה ad Afamya Tata’a until the
lower Afamya. תרתי אפמיא הוו, Tartei Afamya havah, there were two Afamyas.
חד עילייתא, chad Illaita, the upper one, וחד תתייתא vechad Tataita and
the lower one. The upper one was חד כשירה, chad kishera, the
upper one was kosher, וחד פסולה, vechad pesula, the lower one was
invalid. So בבל Bavel only went up to and not including the
lower
אפמיא. Afamya. ובין חדא לחדא פרסה, Uvein chada lechada parsa, and there
was only a פרסה parsa length between the two of them,
which is like four kilometers I think. וקפדי אהדדי. Vekafdi ahaddadi. Is
that right? I think so. Anyway,
וקפדי אהדדי. Vekafdi ahaddadi. And they were מקפיד makpid on one another.
What does that mean they were מקפיד? makpid? Like they didn't want
to have anything to do with one another. Certainly the kosher one
didn't want to have anything to do with the פסול pasul one.
Okay. ואפילו נורא לא מושלי אהדדי, Ve’afilu nura lo mushlei ahaddadi, they
didn't even like borrow like a flame from one another because they
didn't want to, you know,
have it sort of like a, you know, didn't want to intermingle
and wind up marrying. The kosher אפמיא Afamya especially with the same
name wanted to keep separate from the פסול one. וסימנך דפסולה היא
דמשתעי משנית, Vesimanach de’pesula hi demishtai mishnit, and you know that the
פסול one is the one that speaks משנית mishnit because we know
this place משנה mishna was also a מישאן mishan was a place
that was problematic, was מיתא, mesa, was ממזר. לעילא
בפרת עד היכא? Le’eila bi’Ferat ad heicha? North on the Euphrates, how
far north does that go? רב אמר עד אקרא דתולבנקי Rav amar
ad Akra deTulbanki until this place. ושמואל אמר עד גישרא דבי פרת
U’Shmuel amar ad Gishra de’vei Ferat until this bridge of פרת. Perat.
רבי יוחנן אמר עד מעברתא דגיזמא, Rabbi Yochanan amar ad Ma’avarta deGizma,
another place. Okay. לייט אביי ואי תימא רב יוסף אדרב, Lait Abaye
ve’iteima Rav Yosef ad’Rav, so they cursed רב Rav because they said
oh it doesn't go as far as רב Rav. thinks, it doesn't
go as far north. אדרב לייט אדשמואל לא לייט? Ad’Rav lait ad’Shmuel
lo lait? They cursed רב Rav. position and not שמואל? Shmuel's? שמואל
Shmuel's position was even more north than רב. אלא אדרב וכל שכן
אדשמואל. Ella ad’Rav vechol shekein ad’Shmuel. Fine, they cursed רב and certainly
שמואל Shmuel's position. They said that they were taking it too far
north and that the kosher area of בבל Bavel did not extend
that far. So it says, ואיבעית אימא לעולם אדרב לייט אדשמואל לא
לייט. Ve’iba’it eima le’olam ad’Rav lait ad’Shmuel lo lait. Or maybe you
know what, they didn't curse שמואל. Shmuel. וגישרא דבי פרת דתתאי הוה
קאי. Vegishra de’vei Ferat detatta’ei havah kai. That actually when שמואל Shmuel
said his teaching, the גישרא דבי פרת Gishra dei Ferat was actually
lower, more southern. So he did not go as far as רב.
So but the fact that we think it's more north and therefore
we were asking this question. Top of ע"ב עמוד א'. Ayin Beis
Amud Aleph. האידנא הוא דעילויה פרסאי. Idna hu de’illyuyei Parsa’ei. But now
Persians have sort of put this bridge at a higher location, but
שמואל Shmuel actually was saying a lower place than רב. We'll just
go a little bit further. אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף Amar lei
Abaye leRav Yosef said אביי to רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. לגיסא דפרת
עד היכא? Le’gisa de’Ferat ad heicha? Okay, how about on the other
side? On the side of the פרת, Perat, we were talking before
West, how far East to the פרת Perat does it go? אמר
ליה מאי דעתך משום בירם? Amar lei mai da’atach mishum Biram? Why
are you asking because you want to know about בירם Biram which
is to the East of the
פרת? Perat? מיוחסי דפומבדיתא מבירם נסבי. Meyuchasei dePumbedita miBiram nasvei. בירם Biram
is fine. The people of ייחוס yichus of פומבדיתא, Pumbedita, which we
already established was a מיוחס miyuchas place, they married women from
בירם. Biram. אמר רב פפא כמחלוקת ליוחסין כך מחלוקת לגיטין. Amar Rav
Papa kemachloket leyuchasin kach machloket legittin. The same debate of the parameters
of בבל Bavel for יוחסין yuchsin is the parameters of בבל Bavel
for גיטין gittin of whether you have to say בפני נחתם בפני
נחתם. bifanay nechtam bifanay nechtam. You don't really have to say it
from בבל Bavel to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael because they knew the
תורה הלכה halacha in בבל Bavel like they knew it in ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. רב יוסף אמר מחלוקת ליוחסין. Rav Yosef amar machloket
leyuchasin. No, this is only a debate of יוחסין. yuchsin. אבל לגיטין
דברי הכל עד ערבא תניינא דגישרא. Aval legittin divrei hakol ad Arva
Tinyana deGishra. But for גיטין, gittin, everybody agrees it's the second like
lake of the bridge. They knew which lake and which bridge they
were talking about. אמר רמי בר אבא חביל ימא תכלא דבבל. Amar
Rami bar Abba Chavil Yama techla deBavel. This place called חביל ימא
Chavil Yama is like the תכלת, techeiles, is like the is the
cream of בבל. Bavel. שוניא וגוביא תכלא דחביל ימא. Shunya veGuvya techla
deChavil Yama. And
these places within, cities I guess within this region of חביל ימא
Chavil Yama called שוניא Shunya and גוביא, Guvya, they're the crème de
la crème. רבינא אמר אף ציצורא, Ravina amar af Tzitzura, even ציצורא.
Tzitzura. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, similarly, חנן בן פנחס אמר
Chanan ben Pinchas amar חביל ימא תכלא דבבל. Chavil Yama techla deBavel.
חביל ימא Chavil Yama is the cream of בבל. Bavel. שוניא וגוביא
וציצורא תכלא דחביל ימא. Shunya veGuvya veTzitzura techla deChavil Yama.
These places are the crème de la crème. אמר רב פפא והאידנא
ערבו בהו כותאי. Amar Rav Papa veha’idna arevu behu Kutai. And nowadays
כותים Kutim are mixed into that place so they're no longer so
wonderful, so good ייחוס. yichus. ולא היא, Velo hi, but it's not
true. איצטריך ההוא דבעי מיניה ולא יהיב ליה. Itzterich hahu deba’ei mineih
velo yahiv lei. He wanted to marry a woman and they didn't
give it to him. Now one way to read this is that
what's his name, רב פפא Rav Papa wanted to marry a woman
from this place and they're so מיוחס meyuchas and they didn't agree
and therefore he started saying eh they've really got Samaritans there, like
he started raising suspicion. רש"י Rashi says it's very hard to think
that he would be מוציא לעז motzi la’az on a whole place
and we talked before about people that make false claims of ייחוס,
yichus, you know, just out of, you know, petulance because they wouldn't
want to marry a woman. So the better explanation רש"י prefers is
that a Samaritan wanted to marry a woman from there and they
refused, but because the Samaritan was there and so on that led
to the suspicion that there were Samaritans there. Okay. Okay, you can
decide which one you prefer.
One more line and then we'll start, stop,
מאי חבל ימא, Mai Chavel Yama, what does חבל ימא Chavel Yama
mean? אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, or where is חבל ימא?
Chavel Yama? זו פרת דבורסי, Zu Prat DeBorsi, it's this place of
פרת דבורסי, Prat DeBorsi, whatever that is. הוא גברא דאמר להו, Hu
gavra de'amar lehu, אנא מן שוט מישט, ana min Shot Mishat, I'm
from this place שוט מישט. Shot Mishat. אמר רב יצחק נפחא, Amar
Rav Yitzchak Nafcha, אגרא דאמשת שוט מישט בין הנהרות עומדת, Agra d'amshat
Shot Mishat bein hanaharot omedet, it's between the rivers, between Tigris and
Euphrates, therefore it's classic בבל, Bavel, it's good ייחוס. yichus. ובין הנהרות
מאי היא? U'vein hanaharot mai hi? So the Gemara is questioning, what
does that mean? אמר אביי אמר רב חמא בר עוקבא אמר רבי
יוסי ברבי חנינא, Amar Abaye amar Rav Chama bar Ukva amar Rabbi
Yose beribi Chanina, בין הנהרות כגולה ליוחסין. Bein hanaharot kegolah leyuchsin.
Okay, between the rivers is like גולה, Golah, is like פומבדיתא Pumbedita
for יוחסין, yuchsin, that is any place between those rivers is a
good place of ייחוס. yichus.
והיכא קיימא, Ve'heicha kaima, and where exactly is that? אמר רבי
יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, מדיקרא ולעיל, miDikra u'le'eil, from this place דיקרא
Dikra and north. ואמר רבי יוחנן, Ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan, עד מעברא דגיזמא,
ad Ma'avara deGizma, to this מעברא דגיזמא Ma'avara deGizma place. אמר אביי,
רצועה נפקא. retzu'ah nafka. Okay, there's a strip that goes out that
goes ahead and includes this. So this place שוט מישט Shot Mishat
is northern than this place of דיקרא, Dikra,
and even though that's more north than where we said בבל Bavel
usually goes, but there's a strip of בבל Bavel that went to
include this place שוט מישט Shot Mishat and therefore it is considered
part of בבל Bavel and has the status of בין הנהרות. Bein
Hanaharot. Okay, that was extremely long but that got us all caught
up and we will end here for now.